这是关节角速度和末端执行器速度之间的线性关系
This is the linear relationship between joint angle velocity and end effector velocity that
我们刚刚解决了。这里的雅可比矩阵J是一个二乘二矩阵，意思是
we worked out a moment ago. The Jacobian matrix here J is a two by two matrix and that means
反转非常容易，所以我们可以像这样编写表达式。这是什么
that it's very easy to invert, so we can write the expression like this. And what this is
说如果我知道我想要的末端效应器速度，以及我是否可以计算雅可比行列式
saying is if I know the end effector velocity that I want, and if I can compute the Jacobian
矩阵，然后反转它，我可以计算出我需要的关节角度速度
matrix and then invert it, I can work out what joint angle velocities I need in order
实现这种特殊的末端效应器速度，这是一个非常强大的东西。不管
to achieve this particular end effector velocity and this is a very powerful thing. No matter
最终效应器速度是什么，我总能计算出一组关节角速度
what the end effector velocity is, I can always work out a set of joint angle velocities that
会给我那个末端效应器的速度。
will give me that end effector velocity.
我们之前已经研究过Jacobian矩阵对于这个简单的两个连接平面
We've previously worked out what the Jacobian matrix is for this simple, two link, planar
操纵器，因为它只是一个二乘二矩阵，它很容易反转和
manipulator and because it's only a two by two matrix, it's very easy to invert and the
逆看起来像这样。这种逆雅可比行列有一个稍微有问题的方面
inverse looks like this. There's one slightly problematic aspect of this inverse Jacobian
这就是这个术语，当第二个关节角度Q2等于零时，这个是逆的
and that is this term here, when the second joint angle, Q2 is equal to zero, this inverse
雅可比人变得无限。这可能看起来有点不寻常，但有一个漂亮的
Jacobian becomes infinite. That might seem a little bit unusual but there's a pretty
这背后的简单直觉。
simple intuition behind this.
让我们来看看发生这种情况的机器人配置。所以这就是机器人
Let's have a look at the robot configuration where this occurs. So this is what the robot
当Q2等于零时看起来像。而且这种机器人的特殊配置经常是
looks like when Q2 is equal to zero. And this particular configuration of the robot is often
被称为奇异姿态，因为它在雅可比行列中引入了一个奇点
referred to as a singular pose because it introduces a singularity into the Jacobian
机器人矩阵。像这样的机器人配置与a完全相同
matrix of the robot. A robot configuration like this is really exactly the same as a
单链接机器人看起来像这样，所以这是一个只有一个关节的机器人
single link robot that looks like this, so this is a robot which only a single joint
角度。显然，像这样的机器人运动非常非常有限。末端效应器
angle. And clearly a robot like this has got very, very limited motion. The end effector
这里的速度只能与这个蓝色矢量平行。这与之相关
velocity can only ever be parallel to this blue vector here. That is tangential to the
机器人链接的轴。机器人末端执行器不可能在此移动
axis of the robot's link. It's not possible for the robot end effector to move in this
方向，这就是奇点来自的地方。在这个特别的
direction at all and this is where the term singularity comes from. In this particular
机器人的配置，它失去了一定的自由度。机器人中有一个方向
configuration of the robot, it's lost a degree of freedom. There is a direction in the robot's
笛卡尔工作空间，其中末端执行器不可能移动。
Cartesian workspace, in which it is impossible for the end effector to move.
即使关节角度不完全等于零;也许它几乎为零，然后我们
Even if a joint angle in not exactly equal to zero; perhaps it's nearly zero, then we
在机器人能够移动的方向上仍然会有问题。所以一个机器人
will still have problems in the directions that the robot is able to move. So a robot
在这种配置中，将难以在这个特定方向上移动。
in this sort of configuration will find it difficult to move in this particular direction.
我们可以计算雅可比矩阵的行列式，如果它等于零或是否等于零
We can compute the determinant of the Jacobian matrix and if it's equal to zero or if it's
等于小，告诉你机器人有一些运动方向
equal to small, that tells you that there is some motion direction for the robot that
将是困难或尴尬。你可以根据自己的手臂来考虑这一点;那里
will be difficult or awkward. You can think about this in terms of your own arm; there
是一些手臂的配置，你有能力移动几乎相同
are some configurations of the arm where you have the ability to move with almost equal
在许多不同的方向上的速度和你的一些其他配置
velocity in many different directions and there are some other configurations of your
手臂，它真的只能在一个方向上有速度;比如什么时候
arm, where it's really only possible to have velocity in one direction; for instance when
你试图扔球，你把手臂放在你可以拥有的配置中
you're trying to throw a ball, you put your arm into a configuration where you can have
你希望球走的方向的最大速度，但几乎没有速度分量
maximum velocity in the direction you want the ball to go, but almost no velocity component
在与此正交的方向上。
in direction orthogonal to that.
描述这种情况的另一种方式是雅可比的条件数。
Another way to describe this situation is in terms of the condition number of the Jacobian.
条件数是一个标量，我们可以从任何矩阵和条件计算
The condition number is a scalar that we can compute from any matrix and if the condition
数字很​​大表明矩阵接近于单数，这就是它的确定
number is large it indicates that the matrix is close to being singular, that is it's determine
接近于零。您可以考虑雅各比矩阵的这种有问题的情况
is close to zero. You can consider this problematic situation of the Jacobian matrix in terms
它具有小的决定因素或大的条件数。条件号码
of it having either a small determinant or a large condition number. The condition number
可以使用内置函数“cond（）”在MATLAB中计算。
can be computed in MATLAB using the built in function "cond()".